漫威影业
阿富汗  库纳尔省
这气氛像是在送我上军事法庭
I feel like you're driving me to a court-martial.
真是的  我做了什么啊
This is crazy. What did I do?
感觉像是你们会停下车  然后灭了我
I feel like you're going to pull over and snuff me.
怎么  你们不许说话吗
What, you're not allowed to talk?
阿甘哥
Hey, Forrest!
我们可以说话的  先生
We can talk, sir.
好啊  那是对我有意见咯
I see. So it's personal?
不  你让他们害怕
No, you intimidate them.
老天爷  你是个妹子
Good God, you're a woman.
我真是没看出来
I honestly... I couldn't have called that.
我是觉得该道歉  但要的就是这个效果吧
I mean, I'd apologise, but isn't that what we're going for here?
-我要首先把你当成士兵  -我是空军
- I thought of you as a soldier first. - I'm an airman.
你的骨骼结构可真不错
You have, actually, excellent bone structure, there.
我现在眼睛都没法从你身上移开了
I'm kind of having a hard time not looking at you now.
这样奇怪吗
Is that weird?
好啦  笑笑嘛  没事的
Come on, it's okay, laugh.
-先生  我有个问题  -问吧
- Sir, I have a question to ask. - Yes, please.
您真跟去年《马克西姆》男士杂志的
Is it true you went 12 for 12
12位封面女郎都搞过吗
with last year's Maxim cover models?
这问题问得好  是  也不是
That is an excellent question. Yes and no.
三月女郎跟我有日程冲突
March and I had a scheduling conflict,
但幸好  圣诞刊的封面是双胞胎
but fortunately, the Christmas cover was twins.
还有问题吗
Anything else?
你这举手是在开玩笑吧
You're kidding me with the hand up, right?
-我可以跟您合个影吗  -非常可以
- Is it cool if I take a picture with you? - Yes. It's very cool.
好
All right.
可别给发到你的"我的空间"主页上
I don't want to see this on your MySpace page.
拜托  别比黑帮手势
Please, no gang signs.
开玩笑的  举起来吧
No, throw it up. I'm kidding.
和平  我爱和平
Yeah, peace. I love peace.
要是和平了我就没生意了
I'd be out of a job with peace.
快点啊  快按键拍照
Come on. Hurry up. Just click it.
别改设置
Don't change any settings.
-怎么回事  -左侧遇敌
- What's going on? - Contact left!
什么情况
What have we got?
吉米  守住斯塔克
Jimmy, stay with Stark!
-趴下  -嗯
- Stay down! - Yeah.
该死
Son of a bitch!
-等等  给我把枪  -待在这儿
- Wait, wait, wait! Give me a gun! - Stay here!
斯塔克工业
钢铁侠
托尼·斯塔克
Tony Stark.
拉斯维加斯  36小时前
远见家  天才
Visionary. Genius.
美国爱国者
American patriot.
甚至还年少时
Even from an early age,
传奇武器开发者霍华德·斯塔克的儿子
the son of legendary weapons developer Howard Stark
就很快凭其杰出独特的头脑吸引了大众目光
quickly stole the spotlight with his brilliant and unique mind.
四岁时  他搭建了第一块电路板
At age four, he built his first circuit board.
六岁时  他搭建了第一台引擎
At age six, his first engine.
有其父必有其子  六岁的托尼·斯塔克建造出他的首台V8发动机
17岁时  他便以最优成绩从麻省理工学院毕业
And at 17, he graduated summa cum laude from MIT.
托尼·斯塔克  麻省理工学院的机器人神童
之后  一位巨头逝世
Then, the passing of a titan.
霍华德和玛丽亚·斯塔克死于车祸  举国为夫妻哀悼
霍华德·斯塔克终身的朋友和盟友
Howard Stark's lifelong friend and ally,
奥巴代亚·斯坦尼接手
Obadiah Stane, steps in
填补了传奇创始人留下的空缺
to help fill the gap left by the legendary founder,
直到21岁的浪子回归
until, at age 21, the prodigal son returns
新来者  托尼·斯塔克21岁掌权
成为了斯塔克工业的新执行总裁
and is anointed the new CEO of Stark lndustries.
掌握了王国的钥匙后
With the keys to the kingdom,
托尼将父亲的遗产带入了新的时代
Tony ushers in a new era for his father's legacy,
制造了更智能的武器
creating smarter weapons,
先进机器人  卫星瞄准
advanced robotics, satellite targeting.
托尼·斯塔克想拯救世界
如今  托尼·斯塔克
Today, Tony Stark
已改变了武器行业的面目
has changed the face of the weapons industry
他确保了自由  并在全球
by ensuring freedom and protecting America
保护美国和其利益
and her interests around the globe.
作为与斯塔克工业的联络人
As liaison to Stark Industries,
我格外荣幸地能与一位真正的爱国者共事
I've had the unique privilege of serving with a real patriot.
他是我的朋友  也是我的好导师
He is my friend and he is my great mentor.
女士们先生们  我很荣幸能将今年的
Ladies and gentlemen, it is my honour to present
极点奖授予托尼·斯塔克先生
this year's Apogee Award to Mr Tony Stark.
托尼
Tony?
-谢谢  中校  -谢谢救场
- Thank you, Colonel. - Thanks for the save.
这太美了  谢谢  非常感谢大家
This is beautiful. Thank you. Thank you all very much.
这太棒了
This is wonderful.
我不是托尼·斯塔克
Well, l'm not Tony Stark.
但如果我是托尼
But if I were Tony,
我会告诉你们我感到多么荣幸
I would tell you how honoured I feel
以及接受如此高的荣誉
and what a joy it is to receive this very
是多么令人开心
prestigious award.
托尼  要知道
Tony, you know...
托尼最棒的地方  也是他最糟的地方
The best thing about Tony is also the worst thing.
他总在工作
He's always working.
瞧啊
Work it!
这多棒
Come on!
-我们该一直待到早上  -你真是难以置信
- We should just stay till the morning. - You are unbelievable.
糟糕  是他们叫你来的吗
Oh, no! Did they rope you into this?
没谁叫我做什么
Nobody roped me into anything!
-对不起  -但他们跟我说
- I'm so sorry. - But they told me that
如果由我来给你颁奖  你会倍感荣幸
if I presented you with an award, you'd be deeply honoured.
那是当然  是你颁奖  多棒
Of course I'd be deeply honoured. And it's you, that's great.
-我们什么时候颁  -在这儿呢
- So when do we do it? - It's right here.
-再来一轮  -给
- One more round. - Here you go.
在这儿啊  好轻松
There it is. That was easy.
-真对不起  -没关系
- I'm so sorry. - Yeah, it's okay.
看啊  这多特别
Would you look at that? That's something else.
这玩意我还没拿过呢
I don't have any of those floating around.
我们试试运气吧
We're gonna let it ride!
给我点运气吧  祝福一下
Give me a hand, will you? Give me a little something-something.
好  你也来
Okay, you, too.
-我不吹别人的骰子  -来嘛  蜜熊
- I don't blow on a man's dice. - Come on, honey bear.
好嘞  罗德中校扔骰子咯
There it is. Lieutenant Colonel Rhodes rolls! And...
两点  好了
Two craps. Line away.
-就这样了  -这还不算最糟的
- That's what happens. - Worse things have happened.
不会有事的  请帮我把筹码整理好
I think we're gonna be fine. Colour me up, will you?
-我要走了  -好
- This is where I exit. - All right.
明天  别迟到了
Tomorrow, don't be late.
-嗯  没问题  -我说真的
- Yeah, you can count on it. - I'm serious!
我知道
I know, I know.
凯撒的东西给凯撒吧  给
Render unto Caesar that which is Caesar's. There you go.
斯塔克先生  等等  斯塔克先生
Mr Stark! Excuse me, Mr Stark!
克莉丝汀·艾凡哈特  《名利场》杂志的
Christine Everhart, Vanity Fair magazine.
可以问您几个问题吗
Can I ask you a couple of questions?
-她很美  -是吗
- She's cute. - She's all right?
-当然  问吧  -行吗
- Yeah. Okay, go. - It's okay?
您被称为当代达·芬奇
You've been called the da Vinci of our time.
您对此有何看法
What do you say to that?
荒唐  我又不会画画
Absolutely ridiculous. I don't paint.
那您怎么看待你的其他外号
And what do you say to your other nickname?
"死亡商人"
"The Merchant of Death"?
这不算坏
That's not bad.
我猜猜  伯克利毕业的
Let me guess. Berkeley?
其实是布朗大学
Brown, actually.
布朗大学小姐
Well, Ms Brown,
这是个不完美的世界  但我们只有这个世界
it's an imperfect world, but it's the only one we've got.
我向你保证
I guarantee you,
如果哪天再不需要武器来维护和平了
the day weapons are no longer needed to keep the peace,
我会开始为婴儿医院制造建材的
I'll start making bricks and beams for baby hospitals.
这段话常练吗
Rehearse that much?
每晚睡觉前都会对着镜子说
Every night in front of the mirror before bedtime.
-看出来了  -我想让你亲眼见识一下
- I can see that. - I'd like to show you first-hand.
我只想要个严肃的答案
All I want is a serious answer.
好吧  说严肃的  我老爸有个理论
Okay, here's serious. My old man had a philosophy,
"和平就是比对方的棍子大"
"Peace means having a bigger stick than the other guy."
卖棍子的人说这话真讨巧
That's a great line coming from the guy selling the sticks.
我父亲帮忙打败了纳粹
My father helped defeat the Nazis.
他还参与了曼哈顿计划[原子弹]
He worked on the Manhattan Project.
很多人  包括你布朗大学的教授们
A lot of people, including your professors at Brown,
都会认为这叫英雄
would call that being a hero.
也会有很多人称之为战争牟利
And a lot of people would also call that war profiteering.
告诉我  你打算报道我们靠推动医疗科技
Tell me, do you plan to report on the millions we've saved
和改善农业技术
by advancing medical technology
而让千百万人延续寿命  免受饥荒的事吗
or kept from starvation with our intelli-crops?
所有那些突破
All those breakthroughs,
都是由军工提供的资金  亲爱的
military funding, honey.
你这辈子失眠过吗
You ever lose an hour of sleep your whole life?
我愿意跟你失眠几小时
I'd be prepared to lose a few with you.
早上好  现在是早7点
Good morning. It's 7:00 a.m.
马里布气温为22度  少云
The weather in Malibu is 72 degrees with scattered clouds.
冲浪条件不错  海浪到腰和肩之间
The surf conditions are fair with waist-to-shoulder high lines.
高潮时间为上午10:52
High tide will be at 10:52 a.m.
加州  马里布
托尼
Tony?
Hey, Tony?
你无权进入这个区域
You are not authorised to access this area.
-天呐  -那是贾维斯  他是房子的管家
- Jesus. - That's Jarvis. He runs the house.
这是你的衣服  干洗熨烫过了
I've got your clothes here. They've been dry-cleaned and pressed,
外面有辆车在等着你
and there's a car waiting for you outside
会带你去任何你指定的地方
that will take you anywhere you'd like to go.
-你一定是著名的派珀·波茨  -是的
- You must be the famous Pepper Potts. - Indeed I am.
都这么多年了
After all these years,
托尼还让你替他拿干洗衣物
Tony still has you picking up the dry-cleaning.
我做任何斯塔克先生要我做的事
I do anything and everything that Mr Stark requires,
偶尔也包括倒垃圾
including, occasionally, taking out the trash.
没有别的事了吧
Will that be all?
扩展视图
Give me an exploded view.
3号气缸的气压似乎过低了
The compression in cylinder three appears to be low.
记录一下
Log that.
-我这就再试一次  -请别把我的音乐关小
- I'm gonna try again, right now. - Please don't turn down my music.
我再通知你
I'll keep you posted.
你现在应该在去往地球另一边的路上了
You are supposed to be halfway around the world right now.
-她接受得如何  -非常好
- How'd she take it? - Like a champ.
你为什么急着赶我走
Why are you trying to hustle me out of here?
你的航班应该是一个半小时前离开的
Your flight was scheduled to leave an hour and a half ago.
有意思  我以为考虑到那是我的飞机
That's funny, I thought with it being my plane and all,
它会等我到了再出发呢
that it would just wait for me to get there.
托尼  我有几件事要跟你商量
Tony, I need to speak to you about a couple things
然后我就要送你出门了
before I get you out of the door.
如果你还没到  飞机就飞了
Doesn't it kind of defeat the whole purpose
那有自己的飞机
of having your own plane
不就没意义了吗
if it departs before you arrive?
拉里来电
Larry called.
他为杰克逊·波洛克画找到了新买家
He's got another buyer for the Jackson Pollock in the wings.
你还想不想要它
Do you want it? Yes or no.
那是他的"春"期代表作吗
Is it a good representation of his spring period?
不是  斯普林斯是他曾生活工作过的
No. The Springs was actually the neighbourhood in East Hampton
一个东汉普顿社区
where he lived and worked,
-并不是春天的"春"  -是吗
- not "spring" like the season. - So?
我觉得还可以  而且定价过高了
I think it's a fair example. I think it's incredibly overpriced.
我要  买  存起来
I need it. Buy it. Store it.
好  麻省理工学院毕业典礼讲话
Okay. The MIT commencement speech...
6月的事  拜托
Is in June. Please,
别拿还没影的事来唠叨我
don't harangue me about stuff that's way, way, down...
他们在唠叨我  我就答应了
They're haranguing me, so I'm gonna say yes.
反弹或吸收
Deflect it and absorb it.
-别传递给我  -你上机前
- Don't transmit it back to me. - I need you to sign this
-我需要你给这个签字  -你干吗非要赶我走
- before you get on the plane. - What are you trying to get rid of me for?
你有安排吗
What, you got plans?
-事实上  真有  -我不喜欢你有安排
- As a matter of fact, I do. - I don't like it when you have plans.
我生日这天是可以有安排的
I'm allowed to have plans on my birthday.
-今天是你生日吗  -嗯
- It's your birthday? - Yes.
我知道的  这就到了吗
I knew that. Already?
是的  多奇怪啊  跟去年是同一天
Yeah. Isn't that strange? It's the same day as last year.
-拿我的钱给自己买点好东西吧  -买了
- Get yourself something nice from me. - I already did.
-怎么样  -可好了
- And? - It was very nice.
-嗯  -很有品味  谢谢  斯塔克先生
- Yeah. - Very tasteful. Thank you, Mr Stark.
不客气  波茨小姐
You're welcome, Miss Potts.
好了
Okay.
你挺厉害  我刚刚以为甩掉你了
You're good. I thought I lost you back there.
是这样  先生
You did, sir.
我不得不抄穆赫兰道的捷径
I had to cut across Mulholland.
被我甩掉了吧
I got you. I got you.
你什么毛病
What's wrong with you?
-怎么了  -三小时
- What? - Three hours.
忙着接受《名利场》的采访呢
I got caught doing a piece for Vanity Fair.
三小时  你让我在这儿站了三小时
For three hours. For three hours you got me standing here.
现在等你了  走吧  快来
Waiting on you now. Let's go. Come on.
起飞  开始吧
Wheels up! Rock and roll!
-你看什么呢  鸭嘴兽  -没事
- What you reading, platypus? - Nothing.
得了  酸糖娃  别生气嘛
Come on, sour patch. Don't be mad.
我说了  我没生气  我不在乎  好吗
I told you, I'm not mad. I'm indifferent, okay?
-我都道歉了  -早上好  斯塔克先生
- I said I was sorry. - Good morning, Mr Stark.
你不用向我道歉
You don't need to apologise to me.
-我是你的哥们  -我都跟他道歉了  但他
- I'm your man. - I told him I was sorry, but he...
-我现在就是不在乎了  -热毛巾要吗
- I'm just indifferent right now. - Hot towel?
你不尊重自己  所以我知道你不尊重我
You don't respect yourself, so I know you don't respect me.
-我尊重你  -我就是你的保姆
- I respect you. - I'm just your babysitter.
如果你需要换尿布了  谢谢
So, when you need your diaper changed... Thank you.
就告诉我  我去给你拿奶瓶  好吗
Let me know and I'll get you a bottle, okay?
加热下清酒  好吗
Heat up the sake, will you?
-多谢提醒我  -我不是说
- Thanks for reminding me. - No, I'm not talking...
我们不喝酒  我们在工作
We're not drinking. We're working right now.
-吃生鱼片一定要配清酒  -你根本就是
- You can't have sashimi without sake. - You are constitutionally
做不到负责任
incapable of being responsible.
不喝酒才不负责
It would be irresponsible not to drink.
不过是一杯睡前酒
I'm just talking about a nightcap.
热清酒
Hot sake?
好  来两杯  谢谢
Yes, two, please.
不  我不喝  我不要
No. I'm not drinking. I don't want any.
我就这意思
That's what I'm talking about.
我早上起床  穿上军服
When I get up in the morning and I'm putting on my uniform,
知道我认得什么吗
you know what I recognise?
我在镜子里能看到
I see in that mirror that
每一个穿着这军服的人都会照应我
every person that's got this uniform on got my back!
知道吗  我跟你不一样  我不适合
Hey, you know what? I'm not like you. I'm not cut out...
不  你不非得像我一样
No, no. You don't have to be like me!
但你远不止现在的你自己
But you're more than what you are.
抱歉  我现在有点无法集中精神
Can you excuse me if I'm a bit distracted here?
不  你现在不能不集中精神  听我说
No! You can't be distracted right now! Listen to me!
阿富汗  巴格兰空军基地
将军
General.
欢迎  斯塔克先生
Welcome, Mr Stark.
我们很期待您的武器展示
We look forward to your weapons presentation.
谢谢
Thanks.
被恐惧和被尊敬  哪个更好
Is it better to be feared or respected?
要我说  两个都要算过分吗
I say, is it too much to ask for both?
因此  我谦卑地献上斯塔克工业
With that in mind, I humbly present the crown jewel
自由系列的旗舰产品
of Stark Industries' Freedom Line.
这是第一个融入了
It's the first missile system
我们的专利冲击科技的导弹系统
to incorporate our proprietary repulsor technology.
人说最好的武器是不需要使用的武器
They say the best weapon is one you never have to fire.
我尊重地表示不同意
I respectfully disagree.
我更喜欢你只需要使用一次的武器
I prefer the weapon you only have to fire once.
我老爸就这么做  美国就这么做
That's how Dad did it. That's how America does it.
而且到目前一直挺成功
And it's worked out pretty well so far.
找个借口
Find an excuse
发射一次这玩意  我亲自担保
to let one of these off the chain, and I personally guarantee you
坏蛋再也不会想从洞里爬出来了
the bad guys won't even want to come out of their caves.
供您参考  耶利哥
For your consideration, the Jericho.
每笔超过五亿的交易
I'll be throwing one of these in
我送一个这个
with every purchase of 500 million or more.
敬和平
To peace!
-托尼  -奥比  你怎么起来了
- Tony. - Obie, what are you doing up?
不清楚情况我睡不着  展示得怎么样
I couldn't sleep till I found out how it went. How'd it go?
很好  看来圣诞节要提前了
It went great. Looks like it's gonna be an early Christmas.
好样的  伙计  明天见了
Way to go, my boy! I'll see you tomorrow, yeah?
你怎么没穿我送你的睡衣
Why aren't you wearing those pyjamas I got you?
晚安  托尼
Good night, Tony.
-托尼  -抱歉  这辆车是"欢乐马"
- Hey, Tony. - I'm sorry, this is the "Fun-vee."
"悍无聊马"在后面
The "Hum-drum-vee" Is back there.
-好样的  -基地见
- Nice job. - See you back at base.
我劝你别那么做
I wouldn't do that if I were you.
你对我做了什么
What the hell did you do to me?
我做了什么
What I did?
我做的事是救你命
What I did is to save your life.
我已经尽力移除了很多弹片  但还剩不少
I removed all the shrapnel I could, but there's a lot left,
而且它们都在往你的房隔去
and it's headed into your atrial septum.
想看看吗
Here, want to see?
我留了纪念品  看看吧
I have a souvenir. Take a look.
我在我的村子里见过不少这样的伤
I've seen many wounds like that in my village.
我们称他们为将死行尸
We call them the walking dead
因为大概要一周
because it takes about a week
弹片才会进入重要器官
for the barbs to reach the vital organs.
-这是什么  -那是块电磁铁
- What is this? - That is an electromagnet,
连在了汽车电池上
hooked up to a car battery,
它在阻止弹片进入你的心脏
and it's keeping the shrapnel from entering your heart.
没错  笑笑
That's right. Smile.
我们见过一次  在伯尔尼的一场科技大会上
We met once, you know, at a technical conference in Bern.
-我不记得了  -当然了
- I don't remember. - No, you wouldn't.
如果我喝得那么醉  肯定站都站不直
If I had been that drunk, I wouldn't have been able to stand,
更别说就集成电路发表讲话了
much less give a lecture on integrated circuits.
我们在哪
Where are we?
快起来  起来
Come on, stand up. Stand up!
学我的样子做
Just do as I do.
把手举起来
Come on, put your hands up.
那是我的枪  他们怎么弄到的
Those are my guns. How did they get my guns?
你听懂了没  学我的样子做
Do you understand me? Do as I do.
他说"欢迎  托尼·斯塔克  美国历史上
He says, "Welcome, Tony Stark, the most famous mass murderer
最著名的大屠杀犯"
in the history of America."
他很荣幸
He is honoured.
他要你给他建导弹
He wants you to build the missile.
你展示的那个耶利哥导弹
The Jericho missile that you demonstrated.
这个
This one.
我拒绝
I refuse.
托尼
Tony!
斯塔克工业
他问你觉得怎么样
He wants to know what you think.
我觉得你有好多我的武器
I think you got a lot of my weapons.
他说他们有你需要
He says they have everything
拿来建造耶利哥的一切
you need to build the Jericho missile.
他要你列出材料清单
He wants you to make the list of materials.
他说要你立刻开始动手
He says for you to start working immediately,
你做好了  他就放了你
and when you're done, he will set you free.
-不  他不会的  -是啊
- No, he won't. - No, he won't.
他们肯定在找你  斯塔克
I'm sure they're looking for you, Stark.
但在这些山里  他们是找不到你的
But they will never find you in these mountains.
你刚刚看到一切
Look, what you just saw,
那就是你的遗产  斯塔克
that is your legacy, Stark.
你一生的心血  落在那些杀人犯手里
Your life's work, in the hands of those murderers.
你想这样死去吗
Is that how you want to go out?
这就是伟大的托尼·斯塔克的
Is this the last act of defiance
最后反抗吗
of the great Tony Stark?
还是说你要想想办法
Or are you going to do something about it?
我何必还要做点什么
Why should I do anything?
他们无论如何都会杀了你  杀了我
They're going to kill me, you, either way.
就算不  我大概也活不过一周
And if they don't, I'll probably be dead in a week.
那么
Well, then,
这一周就对你至关重要了吧
this is a very important week for you, isn't it?
如果这里要做我的工作站
If this is going to be my work station,
我要灯火通明  这个竖好
I want it well-lit. I want these up.
我需要焊接工具  乙炔和丙烷的都行
I need welding gear. I don't care if it's acetylene or propane.
我需要焊接工作台
I need a soldering station.
头盔  护目镜
I need helmets. I'm gonna need goggles.
我还要熔炼杯  两组精密工具
I would like a smelting cup. I need two sets of precision tools.
斯塔克工业
-你说多少种语言  -好多种
- How many languages do you speak? - A lot.
但看来在这里还是不够用
But apparently, not enough for this place.
他们说阿拉伯语  乌尔都语
They speak Arabic, Urdu,
达里语  帕施图语
dari, Pashto,
蒙古语  波斯语  俄语
Mongolian, Farsi, Russian.
他们是什么人
Who are these people?
他们是你的忠实顾客  先生
They are your loyal customers, sir.
他们自称"十戒组织"
They call themselves the Ten Rings.
如果你告诉我你的计划
You know, we might be more productive
我们的动作可能会更快
if you include me in the planning process.
好吧  我们不需要这个
Okay, we don't need this.
那是什么
What is that?
钯  0.15克
That's palladium, 0.15 grammes.
我们需要至少1.6
We need at least 1.6,
你去把另外11个拆了吧
so why don't you go break down the other 11?
他在干什么
What's he doing?
干活儿
Working.
小心  我们只有一次机会
Careful. Careful, we only get one shot at this.
放心  我手很稳
Relax. I have steady hands.
要不你怎么会还活着
Why do you think you're still alive?
-怎么称呼你  -我叫殷森
- What do I call you? - My name is Yinsen.
殷森  认识你很高兴
Yinsen. Nice to meet you.
我也很高兴认识你
Nice to meet you, too.
那看上去不像耶利哥导弹
That doesn't look like a Jericho missile.
因为那是个迷你方舟反应堆
That's because it's a miniaturised arc reactor.
我家里有个大的给我的工厂供电
I got a big one powering my factory at home.
这应该足以阻止弹片进入我的心脏
It should keep the shrapnel out of my heart.
但它能产生什么
But what could it generate?
如果我没算错  我通常不会算错
If my math is right, and it always is,
每秒能产生3千兆焦耳
three gigajoules per second.
那足以让你的心跳50辈子
That could run your heart for 50 lifetimes.
或者让什么大玩意跑15分钟
Or something big for 15 minutes.
-这是我们逃离的方法  -是什么
- This is our ticket out of here. - What is it?
摊平了看
Flatten them out and look.
厉害
Impressive.
很好
Good.
下得好
Good roll. Good roll.
你还没跟我说你是哪里人
You still haven't told me where you're from.
我来自一个叫科米拉的小镇
I'm from a small town called Gulmira.
-那里其实很不错  -有家人吗
- It's actually a nice place. - Got a family?
有  等我离开这里  就能见到他们
Yes, and I will see them when I leave here.
你呢  斯塔克
And you, Stark?
-没有  -没有吗
- No. - No?
你是个拥有一切的人
So you're a man who has everything
却一无所有
and nothing.
看上去完全不像照片上的东西
It doesn't look anything like the picture.
或许是改装过了
Maybe it's been modified.
尾翼不对
The tail is wrong.
就是倒过来了
It's just backwards.
放松
Relax.
弓和箭
The bow and arrow
曾是武器科技的巅峰
once was the pinnacle of weapons technology.
让伟大的成吉思汗
It allowed the great Genghis Khan
一统从太平洋到乌克兰之间的土地
to rule from the Pacific to the Ukraine.
他的帝国是亚历山大大帝的两倍
An empire twice the size of Alexander the Great
是罗马帝国的四倍
and four times the size of the Roman Empire.
但今天
But today,
有最新的斯塔克工业武器的人
whoever holds the latest Stark weapons
就能统治这些土地
rules these lands.
很快
And soon,
就要轮到我了
it will be my turn.
你为什么让我失望了
Why have you failed me?
我们在工作
We're working.
非常努力
Diligently.
我留了你一命
I let you live.
你就如此回报我吗
This is how you repay me?
工作复杂
It's very complex.
他已经很尽力了
He's trying very hard.
让他跪下
On his knees.
你当我傻吗
You think I'm a fool?
我会问出真相的
I'll get the truth.
我们都在工作
We're both working.
张开嘴
Open your mouth.
他要什么
What does he want?
你当我傻吗
You think I'm a fool?
究竟怎么回事
What's going on?
告诉我实话
Tell me the truth.
他在给你做耶利哥
He's building your Jericho.
你要什么  完成日期吗
What do you want? A delivery date?
我需要他
I need him.
好助手
Good assistant.
明天把我的导弹组装好
You have till tomorrow to assemble my missile.
行吗  你能动吗
Okay? Can you move?
好  再说一遍
Okay, say it again.
正前方41步
41 steps straight ahead.
出门16步右转
Then 16 steps, that's from the door, fork right,
走33步  再右转
33 steps, turn right.
斯塔克呢
Where is Stark?
他刚刚还在的
He was here a moment ago.
去找他
Go look for him.
殷森  殷森  斯塔克
Yinsen! Yinsen! Stark!
说话  对他说句话
Say something. Say something back to him.
他在说匈牙利语
He's speaking Hungarian.
-我不会  -那就说匈牙利语
- I don't... - Then speak Hungarian.
-好吧  我会...  -你会什么
- Okay. I know. - What do you know?
-怎么样  -天呐
- How'd that work? - Oh, my goodness.
-倒是挺成功  -我就这样
- It worked all right. - That's what I do.
-我把这个弄完  -去启动动力程序
- Let me finish this. - Initialise the power sequence.
好
Okay.
-快  -你说
- Now! - Tell me. Tell me.
F11  看到进度条告诉我
Function 11 . Tell me when you see a progress bar.
-应该有了  -有了
- It should be up right now. - Yes.
跟我说  看到了吗
Talk to me. Tell me when you see it.
-有了  -CTRL加I
- I have it. - Press Control "I".
-I  好  -I  回车
- "I." Got it. - "I." "Enter." "I" and "Enter."
过来  给我扣好
Come over here and button me up.
好了
Okay. All right.
六角螺栓  隔一个锁一个
Every other hex bolt.
-他们来了  -很不妙  快完成
- They're coming! - Nothing pretty, just get it done.
-快完成  -他们来了
- Just get it done. - They're coming.
确认关卡都没人了
Make sure the checkpoints are clear
再跟着我出去
before you follow me out, okay?
我们还需要时间
We need more time.
-我去给你争取点时间  -按计划来
- I'm gonna go buy you some time. - Stick to the plan!
按计划来
Stick to the plan!
殷森
Yinsen!
-殷森  -小心
- Yinsen! - Watch out!
斯塔克
Stark.
快点  我们得走了
Come on. We got to go.
动一动啊  我们说好的  按计划来
Move for me, come on. We got a plan. We're gonna stick to it.
我的计划本就是如此  斯塔克
This was always the plan, Stark.
你还得去见家人呢  起来吧
Come on, you're gonna go see your family. Get up.
我的家人都死了
My family is dead.
我要去见他们了  斯塔克
I'm going to see them now, Stark.
没事的
It's okay.
我想要这样的
I want this. I want this.
谢谢你救我
Thank you for saving me.
别浪费  别浪费你的人生
Don't waste it. Don't waste your life.
该我了
My turn.
不赖了
Not bad.
"欢乐马"怎么样
How was the "Fun-vee"?
下次  你跟我一车  好吗
Next time, you ride with me, okay?
小心  看着脚下
Watch it, coming up here.
开玩笑吗  叫他们走开
Are you kidding me with this? Get rid of them.
你的眼睛红了  为失踪已久的老板落泪了吗
Your eyes are red. A few tears for your long-lost boss?
是喜悦的眼泪  我讨厌找工作
Tears of joy. I hate job hunting.
嗯  假期结束了
Yeah, vacation's over.
去哪  先生
Where to, sir?
-去医院  -不
- Take us to the hospital. - No.
谢谢  哈皮  什么叫不  托尼
Please, Happy. No? Tony,
-你得去医院  -不就是不
- you have to go to the hospital. - No is a complete answer.
-得让医生给你看看  -我不非得做什么
- The doctor has to look at you. - I don't have to do anything.
我被囚三个月了
I've been in captivity for three months.
我有两件想做的事
There are two things I want to do.
我要一个美国奶酪汉堡
I want an American cheeseburger,
-还有一件...  -够了
- and the other... - That's enough of that.
不是你想的那件
...is not what you think.
我要你马上召开记者招待会
I want you to call for a press conference now.
-召开记者招待会  -是的
- Call for a press conference? - Yeah.
-为什么啊  -霍根  开车
- What on earth for? - Hogan, drive.
先去找汉堡
Cheeseburger first.
看啊
Look at this!
托尼
Tony.
-我们本想去医院见你的  -我没事
- We were going to meet at the hospital. - No, I'm fine.
看看你
Look at you!
-你非得买个汉堡  -拜托
- You had to have a burger, yeah? - Well, come on.
-给我买了吗  -只剩一个了  我很想吃
- You get me one of those? - There's only one left. I need it.
看看谁来了  好啊
Hey, look who's here! Yeah!
-波茨小姐  -是
- Miss Potts? - Yes.
能跟你说句话吗
Can I speak to you for a moment?
我不参加问答的
I'm not part of the press conference,
但记者招待会马上就开始
but it's about to begin right now.
我不是记者
I'm not a reporter.
我是菲尔·科尔森特工
I'm Agent Phil Coulson,
我隶属国土战略防御攻击
with the Strategic Homeland Intervention, Enforcement
与后勤保障局
and Logistics Division.
-好拗口  -是啊  我们还在改进
- That's quite a mouthful. - I know. We're working on it.
国防部  联调局和中情局
You know, we've been approached already
都已经找过我们了
by the DOD, the FBI, the CIA...
我们是独立部门  目标更明确专一
We're a separate division with a more specific focus.
我们需要询问斯塔克先生
We need to debrief Mr Stark
关于他逃脱的具体情况
about the circumstances of his escape.
-我会加到日程里的  好吗  -谢谢
- I'll put something in the book, shall I? - Thank you.
大家可以坐下吗
Hey, would it be all right if everyone sat down?
你们都坐下吧
Why don't you just sit down?
这样你们都能看到我  我也能...
That way you can see me, and I can...
这样不那么正式
A little less formal and...
-怎么变成嬉皮士聚会了  -别问我
- What's up with the love-in? - Don't look at me.
我不知道他是想干什么
I don't know what he's up to.
-见到你真好  -我也是
- Good to see you. - Good to see you.
我没能跟爸爸说再见
I never got to say goodbye to Dad.
我没能跟我父亲说再见
I never got to say goodbye to my father.
我有些问题想问他
There's questions that I would have asked him.
我想问他对公司的作为怎么看
I would have asked him how he felt about what this company did.
他是否有过挣扎  有过怀疑
If he was conflicted, if he ever had doubts.
或许他就完全是
Or maybe he was every inch
新闻纪录片里的那个男人
the man we all remember from the newsreels.
我看到了年轻的美国人被杀
I saw young Americans killed
杀害他们的正是我为了维护他们而制造的武器
by the very weapons I created to defend them and protect them.
我还看到
And I saw that I
我已经成为了
had become part of a system
不愿负担责任的系统的一员
that is comfortable with zero accountability.
-斯塔克先生  -本
- Mr Stark! - Hey, Ben.
你在那里经历了什么
What happened over there?
我开了眼界  我意识到我可以为
I had my eyes opened. I came to realise that I have more
这世界做更多  而不只是制造爆炸
to offer this world than just making things that blow up.
因此  即刻生效  我要关闭
And that is why, effective immediately, I am shutting down
斯塔克国际公司的武器生产部
the weapons manufacturing division of Stark lnternational
直到
until such a time
我决定好公司的未来
as I can decide what the future of the company will be.
-大家这下不愁  -决定好它的走向
- I think we're gonna be... -  What direction it should take,
-卖不出报纸了  -我能接受的
- selling a lot of newspapers. - one that l'm comfortable with
并且与国家最高利益
and is consistent with the highest good
一致的走向
for this country, as well.
我们应该记住的
What we should take away from this
是托尼回来了
is that Tony's back!
而且非常健康
And he's healthier than ever.
我们将进行内部探讨
We're going to have a little internal discussion
随后向大家通报
and we'll get back to you with the follow-up.
-他人呢  -在里面
- Where is he? - He's inside.
那...挺顺利嘛
Well, that... That went well.
我是在脑后放了个靶子吗
Did I just paint a target on the back of my head?
你的脑袋  那我的脑袋呢
Your head? What about my head?
你觉得明天股价
What do you think the over-under on the stock
会跌到什么程度
drop is gonna be tomorrow?
-乐观估计  40点  -至少
- Optimistically, 40 points. - At minimum.
是啊
Yep.
托尼  我们是武器制造商
Tony, we're a weapons manufacturer.
奥比  我不希望我们将来只留下杀伤数字
Obie, I just don't want a body count to be our only legacy.
这是我们的工作
That's what we do.
我们是铁商  我们制造武器
We're iron mongers. We make weapons.
大楼上是我的名字
It's my name on the side of the building.
我们的工作让世界不会陷入混乱
And what we do keeps the world from falling into chaos.
我看到的可不是这样
Not based on what I saw.
我们做得不够好
We're not doing a good enough job.
我们可以做得更好  我们要做别的
We can do better. We're gonna do something else.
什么别的  你要我们做奶瓶吗
Like what? You want us to make baby bottles?
我认为我们该重新考虑方舟反应堆科技
I think we should take another look into arc reactor technology.
得了  方舟反应堆就是个噱头
Come on. The arc reactor, that's a publicity stunt!
托尼  拜托
Tony, come on.
我们建这个是为了堵嬉皮士的嘴
We built that thing to shut the hippies up!
-成功了  -是啊  作为科学项目
- It works. - Yeah, as a science project.
方舟反应堆的效益性根本不好
The arc was never cost effective.
我们建造之前就知道了
We knew that before we built it.
方舟反应堆科技是个死胡同  是吧
Arc reactor technology, that's a dead end, right?
或许吧
Maybe.
是吧  我们在这方面多久没有突破了
Am I right? We haven't had a breakthrough in that in what?
-30年吗  -据说是的
- Thirty years. - That's what they say.
你的扑克脸能更糟点吗  告诉我  谁说的
Could you have a lousier poker face? Just tell me, who told you?
-别管了  给我看  -罗德还是派珀
- Never mind who told me. Show me. - It's Rhodey or Pepper.
-我要看  -好吧  是罗德
- I want to see it. - Okay, Rhodey.
-好吧  -行吗
- Okay. - Okay?
成功了
It works.
听我说  托尼  我们是一队的  懂吗
Listen to me, Tony. We're a team. Do you understand?
只要我们合力  没什么是做不到的
There's nothing we can't do if we stick together,
就像当年我和你父亲
like your father and I.
抱歉我没提前跟你商量
I'm sorry I didn't give you a heads-up, okay?
-但如果我说了  -托尼
- But if I had... - Tony.
托尼  别再干这种脱口而出的事了
Tony, no more of this "ready, fire, aim" business.
-明白吗  -那是老爸常说的话
- You understand me? - That was Dad's line.
你得让我来处理
You gotta let me handle this.
我们现在得玩另一套把戏了
We're gonna have to play a whole different kind of ball now.
我们要承受很大压力
We're going to have to take a lot of heat.
我要你保证  你会低调些
I want you to promise me that you're gonna lay low.
斯塔克工业
Stark lndustries!
我给你推荐条路  准备好了吗
I've got one recommendation! Ready? Ready?
卖卖卖
Sell, sell, sell!
弃船
Abandon ship!
兴登堡飞艇的事记得吗
Does the Hindenburg ring any bells?
我给大家看看
Let me show you
新斯塔克工业的商业计划
the new Stark lndustries business plan!
这就是一家不造武器的武器公司
Look, that's a weapons company that doesn't make weapons!
派珀  你的手有多大
Pepper. How big are your hands?
-什么  -你的手有多大
- What? - How big are your hands?
-我不懂这...  -下来  我需要你
- I don't understand why... - Get down here. I need you.
伸出来  给我看看你的手
Let's see them. Show me your hands.
给我看看
Let's see them.
好小  好精巧
They are small. Very petite, indeed.
我需要你帮个忙
I just need your help for a sec.
天呐  那就是维系你生命的东西吗
Oh, my God, is that the thing that's keeping you alive?
之前是  现在是古董了
It was. It is now an antique.
这个将在未来一段时间内维系我的生命
This is what will be keeping me alive for the foreseeable future.
我要换升级版的
I'm swapping it up for an upgraded unit,
现在遭遇了点障碍
and I just ran into a little speed bump.
障碍  什么意思
Speed bump, what does that mean?
没事  就是个小问题
It's nothing. It's just a little snag.
这个装置下面有条暴露的电线
There's an exposed wire under this device.
接触到了槽壁
And it's contacting the socket wall
造成了短路
and causing a little bit of a short.
没事的
It's fine.
-你要我做什么  -放在那边桌上
- What do you want me to do? - Put that on the table over there.
-那个没用了  -天呐
- That is irrelevant. - Oh, my God!
你伸手进去
I want you to reach in,
轻轻地把电线拉出来
and you're just gonna gently lift the wire out.
-安全吗  -应该没事
- Is it safe? - Yeah, it should be fine.
就像手术游戏  别让电线
It's like Operation. You just don't let it
碰到槽壁就行  否则就会发出哔声
touch the socket wall or it goes "beep."
什么"手术游戏"
What do you mean, "Operation"?
就是个游戏  算了
It's just a game, never mind.
-轻轻地把电线拉出来  -好
- Just gently lift the wire. - Okay.
好吗  很好
Okay? Great.
我觉得我做这个不够格
You know, I don't think that I'm qualified to do this.
你可以的  你是我认识的最够格
No, you're fine. You're the most capable, qualified,
最值得信赖的人  你会做得很棒的
trustworthy person I've ever met. You're gonna do great.
这个要求太过分了吗  因为我
Is it too much of a problem to ask? 'Cause I'm...
-好吧  -我真的需要你帮忙
- Okay, okay. - I really need your help here.
好了
Okay.
有脓液
Oh, there's pus!
不是脓液
It's not pus.
是装置释放出的无机原生质
It's an inorganic plasmic discharge from the device,
-不是我身体分泌的  -好臭
- not from my body. - It smells!
是啊
Yeah, it does.
铜线  铜线  摸到了吗
The copper wire. The copper wire, you got it?
-好  摸到了  -摸到了吗
- Okay, I got it! I got it! - Okay, you got it?
拉出来时不要碰到槽壁
Now, don't let it touch the sides when you're coming out!
-我之前就是跟你强调这个  -抱歉
- That's what I was trying to tell you before. - I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
拉出来时  一定不要拉出...
Okay, now make sure that when you pull it out, you don't...
最末端的磁铁
There's a magnet at the end of it!
就这个  你给拉出来了
That was it. You just pulled it out.
-天呐  -我没想到...
- Oh, God! - Okay, I was not expecting...
-别放回去  -我怎么办
- Don't put it back in! Don't put it back in! - Okay, what do I do?
怎么了
What's wrong?
没事  我就是要心脏骤停了
Nothing, I'm just going into cardiac arrest
-因为你像捞鱼一样  -什么
- 'cause you yanked - What?
-把它揪出来了  -你不是说挺安全的吗
- it out like a trout... - I though you said it was safe!
我们得快了  拿这个
We gotta hurry. Take this. Take this.
-迅速换好  -好
- You gotta switch it out really quick. - Okay. Okay.
-托尼  -什么
- Tony? - What?
-会没事的  -是吗
- It's going to be okay. - Is it?
不会有事的
It's gonna be okay.
-我会搞定的  -希望如此
- I'm gonna make this okay. - Let's hope.
把那个接到底盘上
Okay, you're gonna attach that to the base plate.
务必要
Make sure you...
很难吗
Was that so hard?
挺好玩的吧
That was fun, right?
好了  给我吧
Here, I got it. I got it. Here.
好样的
Nice.
-你没事吧  -嗯  我很好  你没事吧
- Are you okay? - Yeah, I feel great. You okay?
永远永远永远
Don't ever, ever, ever,
别再要求我做这样的事了
ever ask me to do anything like that ever again.
我只有你
I don't have anyone but you.
好了
Anyway...
-这个你要我怎么处理  -那个吗
- What do you want me to do with this? - That?
毁掉
Destroy it.
焚毁
Incinerate it.
你不想留着吗
You don't want to keep it?
派珀  人们说我有很多特点
Pepper, I've been called many things.
但不包括"怀旧"
"Nostalgic" is not one of them.
没别的事了吧  斯塔克先生
Will that be all, Mr Stark?
没事了  波茨小姐
That will be all, Miss Potts.
笨手笨脚  过来
Hey, Butterfingers, come here.
我桌上这堆东西怎么回事
What's all this stuff doing on top of my desk?
那是我的手机  那是我跟爸爸的合照
That's my phone, that's a picture of me and my dad.
那里  垃圾堆里
Right there. In the garbage. All that stuff.
空中战斗的未来  是有人还是无人
The future of air combat. Is it manned or unmanned?
以我的经验
I'll tell you, in my experience,
无人机永远
no unmanned aerial vehicle
比不过飞行员的直觉
will ever trump a pilot's instinct,
见解
his insight,
以及看透表象
that ability to look into a situation beyond the obvious
确定结果的判断力
and discern its outcome, or a pilot's judgement.
中校  何不让飞行员摆脱飞机
Colonel? Why not a pilot without the plane?
看看是谁从天而降  托尼·斯塔克先生
Look who fell out of the sky. Mr Tony Stark.
-你好  先生  -说到有人无人[是不是男人]
- Hello, sir. - Speaking of manned or unmanned,
你们一定要问他
you gotta get him to tell you
有年春假猜错答案的那次
about the time he guessed wrong at spring break.
记住  春假  1987年
Just remember that, spring break, 1987.
-跟你一起醒来的那位美丽女士  -别闹
- That lovely lady you woke up with. - Don't do that!
-他叫什么来着  -别闹
- What was his name? - Don't do that.
-埃文吗  -别闹
- Was it Ivan? - Don't do that.
他们会信的  别闹
They'll believe it. Don't do that.
-好吧  -别闹
- Okay. - Don't do that.
-认识你们很高兴  -让我们聊会儿
- Pleasure meeting you. - Give us a couple minutes, you guys.
-我很意外  -为什么
- I'm surprised. - Why?
我没想到这么快就能见到你起来走动
I swear, I didn't expect to see you walking around so soon.
我可不止是走动
I'm doing a little better than walking.
-真的  -嗯
- Really? - Yeah.
罗德  我在研究个大项目
Rhodey, I'm working on something big.
我是来找你的  我希望你也参与进来
I came to talk to you. I want you to be a part of it.
你要让这里
You're about to make
很多人开心起来了
a whole lot of people around here real happy,
因为之前记者招待会上的那个表演
'cause that little stunt at the press conference,
太逗了
that was a doozy.
这不是给军队的  我不...这不一样
This is not for the military. I'm not... It's different.
怎么  你成人道主义者了
What? You're a humanitarian now or something?
-我需要你听我说  -不
- I need you to listen to me. - No.
你需要时间把思绪理清楚
What you need is time to get your mind right.
-我说真的  -好吧
- I'm serious. - Okay.
很高兴见到你  托尼
It's nice seeing you, Tony.
谢谢
Thanks.
贾维斯  你在吗
Jarvis, you up?
为您  先生  永远都在
For you, sir, always.
我想建立新项目文档  标注为马克2号
I'd like to open a new project file, index as Mark II.
要将文件存储到斯塔克工业中央数据库中吗
Shall I store this on the Stark lndustries Central Database?
其实  我不知道现在能信任谁
Actually, I don't know who to trust right now.
直到我另说
Till further notice,
先把东西都存在我的私人服务器上吧
why don't we just keep everything on my private server?
在研究秘密项目吗  先生
Working on a secret project, are we, sir?
我不希望这玩意落入坏人之手
I don't want this winding up in the wrong hands.
或许在我手里  它能做好事
Maybe in mine, it can actually do some good.
下一个  上去
Next. Up.
不是靴子  呆呆  这里  懂吗
Not in the boot, Dummy. Right here. You got me?
别动  很好
Stay put. Nice.
你真没用  往下到脚趾  我来吧
You're of no benefit at all. Move down to the toe. I got this.
好吧  对不起  我妨碍你了吗
Okay, I'm sorry, am I in your way?
上去
Up.
算了  别动
Screw it. Don't even move.
你真是个悲剧
You are a tragedy.
好了  我们好好做吧
Okay, let's do this right.
开始量步  半米  正中央
Start mark, half a metre, and back and centre.
呆呆  精神点  准备灭火
Dummy, look alive. You're on standby for fire safety.
你  开拍
You, roll it.
好  启动手动控制
Okay. Activate hand controls.
慢慢开始
We're gonna start off nice and easy.
看看10%的推进能量能否实现上升
We're gonna see if 10% thrust capacity achieves lift.
三
And three,
二
two,
一
one.
上2  好  定位
Up two. All right, set that.
我一直在摁铃  没听到对讲机响吗
I've been buzzing you. Did you hear the intercom?
嗯  都...什么
Yeah, everything's... What?
-奥巴代亚在楼上  -好啊
- Obadiah's upstairs. - Great!
-要我怎么跟他说  -好  我就上去
- What would you like me to tell him? - Great. I'll be right up.
好
Okay.
你不是说你不做武器了吗
I thought you said you were done making weapons.
是的
It is.
这是飞行稳定器  完全无害
This is a flight stabiliser. It's completely harmless.
这我没料到
I didn't expect that.
怎么样
How'd it go?
那么不顺利啊
It went that bad, huh?
就因为我从纽约带了披萨回来
Just because I brought pizza back from New York
不代表就不顺利
doesn't mean it went bad.
当然了  天呐
Sure doesn't. Oh, boy.
如果你去了还能顺利点
It would have gone better if you were there.
你叫我低调的  所以我照做了
You told me to lay low. That's what I've been doing.
我低调  你处理好...
I lay low, and you take care of all...
拜托  那是指在公众  媒体面前
Hey, come on. In public. The press.
这可是董事会会议
This was a board of directors meeting.
是董事会会议吗
This was a board of directors meeting?
董事会称你患了创伤后应激症
The board is claiming you have post traumatic stress.
他们提交了禁止令
They're filing an injunction.
-什么  -他们要阻拦你
- A what? - They want to lock you out.
怎么  因为股票跌了40点吗
Why, 'cause the stocks dipped 40 points?
我们早知道会这样
We knew that was gonna happen.
-是56.5  -这无所谓
- Fifty-six and a half. - It doesn't matter.
我们拥有公司的控股权
We own the controlling interest in the company.
托尼  董事会也有权利
Tony, the board has rights, too.
他们称  你和你的新方向
They're making the case that you and your new direction
-对公司不是最有利的  -我这是负责任
- isn't in the company's best interest. - I'm being responsible!
这是我和公司的新方向
That's a new direction for me, for the company.
我要代表公司
I mean, me on the company's behalf
负起责任
being responsible for the way that...
这真好
This is great.
-得了  托尼  -我去工作室
- Oh, come on. Tony. Tony. - I'll be in the shop.
托尼  听我说
Tony. Listen.
我在努力挽回局面
I'm trying to turn this thing around,
但你得给我点东西
but you gotta give me something.
拿给他们看的东西
Something to pitch them.
让工程师分析下那个
Let me have the engineers analyse that.
画出参数图纸
You know, draw up some specs.
-不行  绝对不行  -让我有根骨头丢给
- No. No, absolutely not. - It'll give me a bone to throw the boys
-这个留在我身上  -纽约的人
- This one stays with me. - in New York!
就是这样  奥比  别想了
That's it, Obie. Forget it.
好  那这个留在我这儿
All right, well, this stays with me, then.
来吧  你可以拿走一块
Go on, here, you can have a piece.
-拿两个吧  -谢谢
- Take two. - Thank you.
我可以下去看看你在做什么吗
You mind if I come down there and see what you're doing?
晚安  奥比
Good night, Obie.
第11天  第37次测试  配置2.0
Day 11 , test 37, configuration 2.0.
因为没有更好的选择
For lack of a better option,
仍由呆呆负责灭火  你再敢喷我
Dummy is still on fire safety. If you douse me again,
而且是我没着火时  我就把你捐给城市学院
and I'm not on fire, I'm donating you to a city college.
慢慢来
All right, nice and easy.
真的  就从1%推进能量开始
Seriously, just gonna start off with 1% thrust capacity.
三  二  一
And three, two, one.
好的
Okay.
别拿那玩意时刻指着我
Please don't follow me around with it, either,
让我觉得我随时会自燃
'cause I feel like I'm gonna catch on fire spontaneously.
退后点  如果真出事了再冲上来
Just stand down! If something happens, then come in.
再来  能量加到2.5%
And again, let's bring it up to 2.5.
三  二  一
Three, two, one.
好吧  我不想到这里来
Okay, this is where I don't want to be!
别烧车
Not the car, not the car!
桌子
Table!
还算可以  没事的
Could be worse! Could be worse! We're fine!
好
Okay.
不
No!
好啊  我能飞了
Yeah, I can fly.
-贾维斯  在吗  -随时候命  先生
- Jarvis, are you there? - At your service, sir.
-启动前置显示  -已启动
- Engage Heads Up Display. - Check.
从本地界面输入偏好
Import all preferences from home interface.
好的  先生
Will do, sir.
好  怎么样
All right, what do you say?
我已经上传好了  先生
I have indeed been uploaded, sir.
我们已经上线  准备好了
We're online and ready.
可以开始虚拟行走吗
Can we start the virtual walk-around?
正在输入偏好  校准虚拟环境
Importing preferences and calibrating virtual environment.
检查控制表面
Do a check on control surfaces.
如您所愿
As you wish.
测试完成  准备关机  开始诊断
Test complete. Preparing to power down and begin diagnostics.
嗯  这样吧  检查天气和航空管制
Yeah. Tell you what. Do a weather and ATC check.
并监听地面控制
Start listening in on ground control.
先生  真正飞行之前
Sir, there are still terabytes
还需要进行兆兆字节的计算
of calculations needed before an actual flight is...
贾维斯  有时候要先跑才能走
Jarvis! Sometimes you got to run before you can walk.
准备好了吗  三  二  一
Ready? In three, two, one.
操作流畅
Handles like a dream.
好了  看看这玩意的本事如何
All right, let's see what this thing can do.
SR-71侦察机的记录是多少
What's SR-71's record?
固定翼飞行的飞行高度记录为8.5万英尺
The altitude record for fixed wing flight is 85,000 feet, sir.
记录就是用来打破的  来啊
Records are made to be broken! Come on!
先生  出现了可能致命的结冰
Sir, there is a potentially fatal buildup of ice occurring.
继续走
Come on!
再高点
Higher!
我们结冰了  贾维斯  展开襟翼
We iced up, Jarvis! Deploy flaps!
贾维斯
Jarvis!
拜托  我们得除冰
Come on, we got to break the ice!
关闭动力
Kill power.
派珀送
托尼·斯塔克有心的证明
记录  主传感器在4万英尺以上变得迟缓
Notes. Main transducer feels sluggish at plus 40 altitude.
壳体增压是个问题
Hull pressurisation is problematic.
我认为结冰可能是影响因素
I'm thinking icing is the probable factor.
观察敏锐  先生
A very astute observation, sir.
或许  如果您打算造访其他星球
Perhaps, if you intend to visit other planets,
我们应该改进排气系统
we should improve the exo systems.
与思科连接  重新配置外壳金属
Connect to the Cisco. Have it reconfigure the shell metals.
使用六翼天使战术卫星的金钛合金
Use the gold titanium alloy from the seraphim tactical satellite.
这样应该能保证外壳不受损
That should ensure a fuselage integrity
而不影响动力-重量比
while maintaining power-to-weight ratio.
-知道了吗  -是
- Got it? - Yes.
我要按提议方案进行渲染吗
Shall I render using proposed specifications?
好好发挥吧
Thrill me.
今晚迪士尼音乐厅的
Tonight's red-hot red carpet is right here
红毯异常火热
at the Disney Concert Hall,
托尼·斯塔克第三届年度
where Tony Stark's third annual
消防员家属基金会慈善晚会在此举办
benefit for the Firefighter's Family Fund
洛杉矶上流社会蜂拥而至
has become the place to be for L.A.'s high society.
贾维斯  我们收到邀请了吗
Jarvis, we get an invite for that?
我没有邀请的记录  先生
I have no record of an invitation, sir.
自从那场怪异
...hasn't been seen in public
且极具争议的记者招待会后就未曾公开露面
since his bizarre and highly controversial press conference.
有些人称他患有创伤后应激症
Some claim he's suffering from post traumatic stress
已经卧床数周  不管真相如何
and has been bedridden for weeks. Whatever the case may be,
没有人指望他今晚出现
no one expects an appearance from him tonight.
渲染已完成
The render is complete.
有点招摇了吧
A little ostentatious, don't you think?
我怎么想的  您一般都很低调的
What was I thinking? You're usually so discreet.
这样吧  加上点火红色
Tell you what. Throw a little hot-rod red in there.
嗯  这样就低调了
Yes, that should help you keep a low profile.
渲染完成
The render is complete.
我喜欢  制造上色吧
Hey, I like it. Fabricate it. Paint it.
开始自动组装
Commencing automated assembly.
估计完成时间  五小时
Estimated completion time is five hours.
别等我了  亲爱的
Don't wait up for me, honey.
武器制造
Weapons manufacturing
只是斯塔克工业的一小部分
is only one small part of what Stark Industries is all about,
我们与火灾救援群体的合作
and our partnership with the fire and rescue community...
-托尼  记得我吗  -完全不
- Hey, Tony, remember me? - Sure don't.
气色真不错  海夫
You look great, Hef.
这一季我们会表现出色的
We're going to have a great quarter.
这世界是怎么了
What's the world coming to
来自己的派对都没有请柬
when a guy's got to crash his own party?
看看你
Look at you.
真是意外
Hey, what a surprise.
里面见
I'll see you inside.
听着  悠着点
Listen, take it slow, all right?
我觉得我已经安抚好董事会了
I think I got the board right where we want them.
好嘞  我就是憋坏了  就玩一会儿
You got it. Just cabin fever. I'll just be a minute.
给我杯威士忌  我饿死了
Give me a Scotch. I'm starving.
斯塔克先生
Mr Stark?
-怎么  -科尔森特工
- Yeah? - Agent Coulson.
是啊  你是那个...
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. The guy from the...
国土战略防御
Strategic Homeland Intervention,
攻击与后勤保障局
Enforcement and Logistics Division.
天呐  你们需要新名字了
God, you need a new name for that.
是啊  我常听人这么说
Yeah, I hear that a lot.
听着  我知道您现在一定很不容易
Listen, I know this must be a trying time for you,
但我们需要了解情况
but we need to debrief you.
还有很多问题未得到解答
There's still a lot of unanswered questions,
这种事情  时间有时很重要
and time can be a factor with these things.
我们约个时间吧
Let's just put something on the books.
24日晚7点在斯塔克工业见如何
How about the 24th at 7:00 p.m. at Stark Industries?
这样吧  说定了  你说得很对
Tell you what. You got it. You're absolutely right.
我去找我助理  定个日子
Well, I'm going to go to my assistant, and we'll make a date.
你太美了  我都没认出你来
You look fantastic! I didn't recognise you.
-你怎么来了  -回避政府特工
- What are you doing here? - Just avoiding government agents.
-你一个人来的吗  -嗯  裙子哪来的
- Are you by yourself? - Yes. Where'd you get that dress?
-是生日礼物  -太棒了
- Oh, it was a birthday present. - That's great.
-你送的  -我的品位真棒
- From you, actually. - Well, I got great taste.
是啊
Yes.
-想跳舞吗  -不
- You want to dance? - Oh, no.
-来嘛  -谢谢了  不
- All right, come on. - Thank you. No.
我让你不舒服了吗
Am I making you uncomfortable?
没有
No. No.
我总忘记擦除臭剂
I always forget to wear deodorant
还当着我所有同事的面穿一件露背裙子
and dance with my boss in front of everyone that I work with
跟我的老板跳舞
in a dress with no back.
-你很美  也很香  -天呐
- You look great and you smell great. - Oh, God.
但如果能让你舒服点  我可以解雇你
But I could fire you if that would take the edge off.
我觉得没了我你恐怕都不会系鞋带了
I actually don't think that you could tie your shoes without me.
-我能撑一周  -是吗
- I'd make it a week. - Really?
-绝对的  -你的社保号码是多少
- Sure. - What's your Social Security number?
-五  -五
- Five. - Five?
-好吧  -嗯
- Right. - Right.
-你漏了几位数字  -另外八个吗
- You're missing just a couple of digits there. - The other eight?
另外八个有你嘛
So I got you for the other eight.
-出去透口气吧  -嗯  我需要透口气
- How about a little air? - Yes, I need some air.
-那感觉太怪了  -完全没关系
- That was totally weird. - Totally harmless.
才不是没关系
It was totally not harmless, by the way.
我们跳了支舞
We're dancing.
-都没人看  -我的所有同事
- No one's even watching. - Everybody who I work with...
不是的  知道为什么吗
No, you know why?
我觉得你不够客观
I think you lost objectivity.
我觉得他们就是...人而已
I think they just... People...
我们就是跳了个舞
We just danced.
不  不只是跳舞
No, it was not just a dance.
你不懂  因为你是你
You don't understand because you're you.
所有人都清楚你是什么样的人
And everybody knows exactly who you are
你怎么对待女人什么的
and how you are with girls and all of that,
这没什么关系
which is completely fine.
但我  你是我的老板
But, you know, then me, you're my boss,
我跟你跳舞
and I'm dancing with you.
-我觉得没人会那么想的  -这让我显得
- I don't think it was taken that way. - Because it makes me look like
好像在
the one who's trying to...
-我觉得你想多了  -我们又来到这里
- I just think you're overstating it. - You know, and we're here,
我还穿着这件荒唐的
and then I'm wearing this ridiculous
裙子  我们还那样跳舞
dress, and then we were dancing like that and...
-我想喝杯酒  谢谢  -好嘞
- I would like a drink, please. - Got it, okay.
-伏特加马丁尼  谢谢  -好
- I would like a vodka martini, please. - Okay.
不加水  要很多橄榄
Very dry with olives, a lot of olives.
至少三颗
Like, at least three olives.
两杯伏特加马丁尼
Two vodka martinis,
不加水  多加橄榄  赶快
extra dry, extra olives, extra fast.
其中一杯加橄榄汁
Make one of them dirty, will you?
托尼·斯塔克
Tony Stark.
居然在这里见到了你
Fancy seeing you here.
-卡莉  -克莉丝汀
- Carrie. - Christine.
没错
That's right.
你今晚居然敢来
You have a lot of nerve showing up here tonight.
你至少能给个反应吗
Can I at least get a reaction from you?
慌张  我认为我的反应是慌张
Panic. I would say panic is my reaction.
我是指你公司与最近
'Cause I was referring to your company's
一宗惨案的关系
involvement in this latest atrocity.
是啊  他们向我发了邀请
Yeah. They just put my name on the invitation.
我不知道能说什么
I don't know what to tell you.
我真的差点相信了
I actually almost bought it, hook, line and sinker.
我出门了几个月  没听说吗
I was out of town for a couple months, in case you didn't hear.
这就是你所谓的负责任吗
Is this what you call accountability?
这里叫科米拉  听说过吗
It's a town called Gulmira. Heard of it?
斯塔克工业
-这是什么时候拍的  -昨天
- When were these taken? - Yesterday.
-我没有准许运输  -你的公司准许了
- I didn't approve any shipment. - Well, your company did.
我不是我的公司
Well, I'm not my company.
-请回避一下  -你见过这些照片吗
- Please, do you mind? - Have you seen these pictures?
-科米拉发生了什么  -托尼
- What's going on in Gulmira? - Tony, Tony.
你不能这么天真
You can't afford to be this naive.
我曾经很天真
You know what? I was naive before,
他们说  "这条线  我们不要越过
when they said, "Here's the line. We don't cross it.
我们就这么做生意"
This is how we do business."
如果我们暗地里做了两面派  我们有吗
If we're double-dealing under the table... Are we?
托尼  拍张照吧
Tony, your picture, please!
我们拍张照吧  来吧
Let's take a picture. Come on.
拍照片了
Picture time!
托尼  你以为是谁排挤了你
Tony. Who do you think locked you out?
是我提出了针对你的禁止令
I was the one who filed the injunction against you.
只有这样我才能保护你
It was the only way I could protect you.
不
No. No.
到达科米拉外围的15英里路程
The 15-mile hike to the outskirts of Gulmira
只能被形容为堕入地狱之路
can only be described as a descent into hell,
进入当代的黑暗之心
into a modern day Heart of Darkness.
来自和平村庄的普通的农民和牧民
Simple farmers and herders from peaceful villages
被迫离开家园
have been driven from their homes,
被军阀赶出了他们的土地
displaced from their lands by warlords
新得的力量为这些人壮了胆
emboldened by a new-found power.
村民们被迫居住在
Villagers have been forced to take shelter
其他村庄的废墟中
in whatever crude dwellings they can find
简陋的遮蔽处里
in the ruins of other villages,
或是躲在这栋旧苏联冶炼厂遗址里
or here in the remnants of an old Soviet smelting plant.
最近的暴力事件
Recent violence has been
被归咎于一群外国士兵
attributed to a group of foreign fighters
他们被当地人称为十戒组织
referred to by locals as the Ten Rings.
可以看到  他们军备齐全  而且目的明确
As you can see, these men are heavily armed and on a mission.
任何妨碍了他们的人
A mission that could prove fatal
都可能因此丧命
to anyone who stands in their way.
因为没有政治干预或国际压力
With no political will or international pressure,
这些难民希望渺茫
there's very little hope for these refugees.
我身边的一个女人  在焦急等待丈夫的消息
Around me, a woman begging for news on her husband,
他被叛乱分子绑架了
who was kidnapped by insurgents,
不知是被强迫加入他们的军队...
either forced to join their militia...
焦急的难民抓着泛黄的照片
Desperate refugees clutch yellowed photographs,
给任何愿意驻足的人看
holding them up to anyone who will stop.
孩子简单的问题  "我的妈妈爸爸在哪"
A child's simple question, "Where are my mother and father?"
难民们希望渺茫
There's very little hope for these refugees,
难民们只能想着  是否会有人来帮忙
refugees who can only wonder who, if anyone, will help.
快点
Hurry it up.
把女人赶上车
Put the women in the trucks.
把武器存放在这里
Stack the weapons here.
把房子清空
Clear all the houses.
那个  快点
That one there. Faster. Faster.
抓住那家伙
Grab that dog.
把他跟其他人放在一起
Put him with the others.
这怎么回事
What the hell is this?
打死这家伙
Shoot this dog.
你们这群没用的东西
You're all incompetent.
脑袋转过去
Turn your head.
他交给你们了
He's all yours.
那是什么玩意  我们准许去那里了吗
What the hell was that? Were we cleared to go in there?
加州  爱德华兹空军基地
没有  长官  他们用了人肉盾
No, sir, they were using human shields.
我们没获得批准
We never got the green light.
给我接国务院  肯定是他们搞的
Put me through to State. They're going to be all over this.
调出显示
Get those monitors up!
发现不明物体
We got a bogey!
-不是空军  -接通中情局了吗
- Wasn't Air Force! - We got the CIA on the line?
我接通了兰利  他们还问是不是我们
I've got Langley on the line. They want to know if it's us.
绝对不是我们  长官
No, it definitely is not us, sir!
-不是海军  -不是陆战队
- It wasn't Navy. - Wasn't Marines.
我需要答案  能拿到目标图像吗
I need answers! Can I please get eyes on target?
-不能  -无法识别
- Negative, negative. - Cannot identify.
马上把武器研发的罗德中校叫来
Get me Colonel Rhodes from Weapons Development down here now!
我们查了身份
We ran an ID check
并交叉对比了所有已知数据库
and cross-referenced with all known databases.
毫无发现
We have nothing.
当地有高空监控吗
Any high altitude surveillance in the region?
当地有空中早期预警和全球鹰
We got an AWAC and a Global Hawk in the area.
这玩意是突然冒出来的吗
So this thing just appeared out of nowhere?
怎么会没在雷达上发现
How come it didn't show up on the radar?
只有很小的雷达截面  长官
Got a minimal radar cross-section, sir.
-隐形的吗  -不是  长官  它很小
- Is it stealth? - No, sir, it's tiny.
应该是无人机
We think it's an unmanned aerial vehicle.
中校  这是什么情况
Colonel, what are we dealing with here?
-我去打个电话  -中士  清条线路
- Let me make a call. - Sergeant, clear a hole.
-喂  -托尼
- Hello? - Tony?
-谁啊  -罗德
- Who's this? - It's Rhodes.
-抱歉  谁  -我说是罗德
- Sorry, hello? - I said it's Rhodes.
-请大点声  -那是什么噪音
- Speak up, please. - What in the hell is that noise?
嗯  我敞篷开车呢
Oh, yeah, I'm driving with the top down.
我现在需要你帮忙
Yeah, well, I need your help right now.
天道好轮回啊
It's funny how that works, huh?
是啊  是这样
Yeah. Speaking of funny,
有个武器站刚被炸毁了
we've got a weapons depot that was just blown up
离你当初被囚的地方只有几公里
a few clicks from where you were being held captive.
那里挺危险的
Well, that's a hot spot.
似乎是有人插手替你完成了工作  是吧
Sounds like someone stepped in and did your job for you, huh?
你为什么气喘吁吁的  托尼
Why do you sound out of breath, Tony?
我没有  我在峡谷里慢跑呢
I'm not, I was justjogging in the canyon.
-你不是在开车吗  -是啊  我开车
- I thought you were driving. - Right, I was driving
到了峡谷  然后去慢跑
to the canyon, where I'm going to jog.
你在那一带真没有什么
You sure you don't have any tech
我应该知道的东西吗
in that area I should know about?
-没有  -发现不明物体了
- Nope! - Bogey spotted!
鞭子战机  正在前往
Whiplash, come in hot.
很好  因为我眼前就有个东西
Okay, good, 'cause I'm staring at one right now,
马上要被炸飞了
and it's about to be blown to kingdom come.
我该撤了
That's my exit.
战情室  这里是鞭子一号
Ballroom, this is Whiplash One.
我看到不明物体了
I've got the bogey in my sights.
鞭子一号  那是什么玩意
Whiplash One, what is it?
我不知道
I've got no idea.
-能进行无线电联络吗  -无反应  长官
- You have radio contact? - Non responsive, sir.
那你可以交火
Then you are clear to engage.
超音速飞行
启动
Hit it.
不明物体刚进入了超音速  我锁定了
That bogey just went supersonic. I got a lock!
-导弹来袭  -照明弹
- lnbound missile. - Flares!
等等  不明物体调用了照明弹
Wait a second. Bogey deployed flares!
展开襟翼
Deploy flaps!
我去
Holy!
那玩意从雷达上消失了  长官
That thing just jumped off the radar, sir.
卫星盯丢了
The sat visual has been lost.
那绝不是无人机
No way that's a UAV.
是什么
What is it?
我什么都看不到
I can't see anything.
不管是什么  刚刚已经死了
Whatever it was, it just bought the farm.
不明物体应该已经被处理掉了  长官
I think bogey's been handled, sir.
-喂  -罗德  是我
- Hello? - Hi, Rhodey, it's me.
-谁  -抱歉  确实是我
- It's who? - I'm sorry, it is me.
你问了  你问的那个就是我
You asked. What you were asking about is me.
瞧  这不是游戏
No, see, this isn't a game.
你不能把平民装备飞入我的活动战区
You do not send civilian equipment into my active war zone.
-你懂不懂  -不是一件装备
- You understand that? - This is not a piece of equipment.
我在里面呢  是件战衣  那是我
I'm in it. It's a suit. It's me!
罗德  你查到什么了吗
Rhodey, you got anything for me?
-标记位置  回基地  -收到  战情室
- Mark your position and return to base. - Roger that, Ballroom.
在你底下
On your belly!
像是个人
lt looks like a man!
甩掉他  翻滚
Shake him off! Roll! Roll!
我被打中了
I'm hit! I'm hit!
确认  他被击中了
It's confirmed. He has been hit.
跳伞
Punch out! Punch out!
鞭子一号坠机
Whiplash One down.
鞭子二号  看到降落伞了吗
Whiplash Two, do you see a chute?
没有  没有降落伞
Negative! No chute, no chute!
我的降落伞卡住了
My chute's jammed!
长官  我看到不明物体了
Sir, I've got a visual on the bogey.
鞭子二号  再次出击
Whiplash Two, reengage.
如果能击落  就击落
If you get a clear shot, you take it.
少校  我们都不知道那是什么
Major, we don't even know what we're shooting at.
让猛禽回来
Call off the Raptors.
那玩意刚在合法禁飞区内
That thing just took out an F- 22
击落了一架F22
inside a legal no fly zone!
鞭子二号  如果能击落  就击落
Whiplash Two, if you have a clear shot, take it!
你又被锁定了  进行躲避操作
You've been reengaged. Execute evasive manoeuvre.
继续飞
Keep going!
降落伞打开
Good chute! Good chute!
-托尼  你还在吗  -谢谢了
- Tony, you still there? - Hey, thanks.
天呐  你个疯子
Oh, my God, you crazy son of a bitch.
你欠我架飞机  你知道吧
You owe me a plane. You know that, right?
严格讲  是他撞了我
Yeah, well, technically, he hit me.
你要过来看看我在做什么吗
Now are you going to come by and see what I'm working on?
不要  我知道得越少越好
No, no, no, no, no, no, the less I know, the better.
我要怎么跟媒体讲
Now, what am I supposed to tell the press?
演练  一般不都用这套屁话吗
Training exercise. Isn't that the usual BS?
没那么简单
It's not that simple.
昨天一架猛禽F22
An unfortunate training exercise
在演练中不幸发生事故
involving an F-22 Raptor occurred yesterday.
庆幸的是  飞行员并未受伤
I am pleased to report that the pilot was not injured.
至于科米拉村庄意料之外的局势反转
As for the unexpected turn of events on the ground in Gulmira,
是谁或是什么进行了干预  我们尚不清楚
it is still unclear who or what intervened,
但我可以保证
but I can assure you that
此事与美国政府无关
the United States government was not involved.
的确很贴身  先生
It is a tight fit, sir.
先生  您越是扭动  就会越疼
Sir, the more you struggle, the more this is going to hurt.
温柔点  这是我第一次
Be gentle. This is my first time.
我设计它能脱下来的  所以
I designed this to come off, so...
我真的应该能
I really should be able to...
请尽量不要动  先生
Please, try not to move, sir.
怎么回事啊
What's going on here?
承认吧
Let's face it.
这不是你撞见我做的最糟糕的事
This is not the worst thing you've caught me doing.
那是弹孔吗
Are those bullet holes?
欢迎
Welcome.
托尼·斯塔克的赠礼
Compliments of Tony Stark.
如果你当初按计划杀了他
If you'd killed him when you were supposed to,
也不会把脸烧掉了
you'd still have a face.
你给我们点小钱杀一位王子
You paid us trinkets to kill a prince.
带我去看武器
Show me the weapon.
来吧  让守卫留在外面
Come. Leave your guards outside.
他的逃脱带来了意外的收获
His escape bore unexpected fruit.
他就是这么做到的
So this is how he did it.
这只是首次的粗糙的尝试
This is only a first, crude effort.
斯塔克已完善了他的设计
Stark has perfected his design.
他制作了一件死亡杰作
He has made a masterpiece of death.
有十几件这种战衣的人  能统治亚洲
A man with a dozen of these can rule all of Asia.
你梦想夺下斯塔克的王位
And you dream of Stark's throne.
我们有共同的敌人
We have a common enemy.
如果我们还在合作
If we are still in business,
我会把设计给你
I will give you these designs
当做礼物
as a gift.
作为交换
And in turn,
希望你能礼尚往来
I hope you'll repay me
给我钢铁战士
with a gift of iron soldiers.
这是你唯一会得到的礼物
This is the only gift you shall receive.
科技
Technology.
在世界的这一带一直是个致命弱点
It's always been your Achilles' heel in this part of the world.
别担心  只会持续15分钟
Don't worry. It'll only last for 1 5 minutes.
这是你最不需要担心的事了
That's the least of your problems.
把装甲和其余的装箱带走
Crate up the armour and the rest of it.
好  我们做个了结吧
All right, let's finish up here.
让方舟反应堆下的16区做好准备
Set up Sector 16 underneath the arc reactor,
我需要遮蔽这些数据
and I'm going to want this data masked.
找来我们最好的工程师
Recruit our top engineers.
马上给我造个原型机
I want a prototype right away.
你忙吗  可以替我去办件事吗
You busy? You mind if I send you on an errand?
我需要你去我办公室
I need you to go to my office.
黑入主机
You're going to hack into the mainframe
拿到所有最近的运输清单
and you're going to retrieve all the recent shipping manifests.
这是锁定芯片
This is a lock chip.
能让你黑进去
This'll get you in.
大概是在执行文档里
It's probably under Executive Files.
要不  就是在幽灵驱动上
If not, they put it on a ghost drive,
那样的话  你就得查找标题数码最小的
in which case you need to look for the lowest numeric heading.
如果我拿回了信息
And what do you plan to do with this information
你打算怎么做呢
if I bring it back here?
还是那套
Same drill.
他们在暗箱操作  我要阻止他们
They've been dealing under the table, and I'm going to stop them.
我要找到我的武器  摧毁它们
I'm going to find my weapons and destroy them.
托尼
Tony,
你知道我愿帮你做任何事
you know that I would help you with anything,
但如果你又要这么胡来  我就不能帮你
but I cannot help you if you're going to start all of this again.
除了这个  别无其他  没有艺术馆开幕
There is nothing except this. There's no art opening.
或是慈善晚会  或是签什么字
There is no benefit. There is nothing to sign.
只有下一项任务  没有别的
There is the next mission and nothing else.
是吗
Is that so?
那我辞职
Well, then, I quit.
这么多年来  你一直在我身边
You stood by my side all these years
看着我收获毁灭的利益
while I reaped the benefits of destruction.
现在我想保护那些
And now that I'm trying to protect the people
因我而身陷危险的人  你却要走人吗
that I put in harm's way, you're going to walk out?
你会害死自己的  托尼
You're going to kill yourself, Tony.
我不要助你一臂之力
I'm not going to be a part of it.
我本不该活下来的
I shouldn't be alive,
除非这有什么意义
unless it was for a reason.
我没疯  派珀
I'm not crazy, Pepper.
我就是终于知道  我该做什么了
I just finally know what I have to do.
我心里知道  这是对的
And I know in my heart that it's right.
你也是我的一切了
You're all I have, too, you know.
警告  安全漏洞
准许访问
找到幽灵驱动
16区  读取文档
16区
Sector 16?
你在干什么  奥巴代亚
What are you up to, Obadiah?
翻译
你可没说你付钱叫我们杀的目标
You did not tell us that the target you paid us to kill
是了不起的托尼·斯塔克
was the great Tony Stark.
-你可以看到  -天呐
- As you can see, - Oh, my God.
奥巴代亚·斯坦尼
Obadiah Stane...
你的欺骗和谎言会让你付出高额代价
...your deception and lies will cost you dearly.
杀托尼·斯塔克的价钱刚刚涨了
The price to kill Tony Stark has just gone up.
开始复制
那么  我们要怎么办
So, what are we going to do about this?
我理解你现在的处境  派珀
I know what you're going through, Pepper.
托尼  他的东西总是好的  是吧
Tony. He always gets the good stuff, doesn't he?
他回家时我好开心
I was so happy when he came home.
就好像他死而复生了
It was like we got him back from the dead.
现在我意识到
Now I realise,
托尼其实根本没有回家来  是吧
well, Tony never really did come home, did he?
他把自己的一部分留在了那个洞里
He left a part of himself in that cave.
伤透了我的心
Breaks my heart.
他是个复杂的人
Well, he's a complicated person.
他经受了很多事  我觉得他会没事的
He's been through a lot. I think he'll be all right.
你真是个少见的女人
You are a very rare woman.
托尼不知道自己多么幸运
Tony doesn't know how lucky he is.
谢谢你  谢谢
Thank you. Thanks.
我得回去了
I'd better get back there.
那是今天的报纸吗
Is that today's paper?
是啊
Yes.
能给我看看吗
Do you mind?
-没问题  -填字谜
- Not at all. - Puzzle.
当然
Of course.
保重
Take care.
下载完成
波茨小姐  我们预约好的
Ms Potts? We had an appointment.
你忘记了我们的约会吗
Did you forget about our appointment?
没有  就现在  跟我来
Nope, right now. Come with me.
-现在  -我们现在就谈
- Right now? - We're going to have it right now.
-对  跟我走  -好
- Yeah, walk with me. - Okay.
我要跟你好好谈谈  包你一辈子不忘
I'm going to give you the meeting of your life.
去你办公室
Your office.
我们一直在尽力而为
Yeah, we've been working our best to do it.
当然  我们...我回头打给你
Absolutely, we're... I'm going to have to call you back.
斯坦尼先生
Mr Stane?
先生  我们尝试了您的要求
Sir, we've explored what you've asked us,
但似乎遇到了点小小障碍
and it seems as though there's a little hiccup.
-其实  -障碍
- Actually... - A hiccup?
是的  为给战衣供能
Yes, to power the suit,
先生  那种科技尚不存在
sir, the technology actually doesn't exist.
-所以  -等等  科技
- So it's... - Wait, wait, wait. The technology?
威廉  这就是那个科技
William, here is the technology.
我只是叫你把它造小点
I've asked you to simply make it smaller.
好  先生  我们也在努力尝试
Okay, sir, and that's what we're trying to do,
但老实说  这不可能
but honestly, it's impossible.
托尼·斯塔克在一个山洞里就造成了
Tony Stark was able to build this in a cave!
用的是一堆破烂
With a box of scraps!
对不起  我不是托尼·斯塔克
Well, I'm sorry. I'm not Tony Stark.
派珀·波茨来电
托尼
Tony?
托尼  你在吗  喂
Tony, are you there? Hello?
呼吸
Breathe.
放松
Easy, easy.
你记得这个吧
You remember this one, right?
真可惜政府没批准
It's a shame the government didn't approve it.
诱发短暂麻痹用途多广泛啊
There's so many applications for causing short-term paralysis.
托尼
Tony.
我找人杀你时
When I ordered the hit on you,
我还担心
I worried that I was
我是杀了金鹅
killing the golden goose.
但是
But, you see,
那真是
it was just
命运  你偏偏活了下来
fate that you survived that.
你还要给出最后一枚金蛋
You had one last golden egg to give.
你真以为
Do you really think
你想了个点子  它就是你的了吗
that just because you have an idea, it belongs to you?
你父亲
Your father,
他帮忙造了原子弹
he helped give us the atomic bomb.
如果他像你这么自私
Now, what kind of world would it be today
现在的世界会是什么样啊
if he was as selfish as you?
真是美丽
Oh, it's beautiful.
西方迷信
贝多芬创作完成第九交响乐后不久便离世
他之后的很多作曲家也都是如此
托尼  这是你的第九交响乐
Tony, this is your Ninth Symphony.
真是杰作  看啊
What a masterpiece. Look at that.
这是你的遗产
This is your legacy.
新一代的武器
A new generation of weapons
将有它作为心脏
with this at its heart.
这些武器会把世界拉回正轨
Weapons that will help steer the world back on course,
让权力落在我们手中
put the balance of power in our hands.
合适的手中
The right hands.
真希望你能看到我的原型机
I wish you could see my prototype.
虽然不像
It's not as...
不像你的那个那么保守
Well, not as conservative as yours.
可惜你还把派珀卷了进来
Too bad you had to involve Pepper in this.
我本来更想留她一命的
I would have preferred that she lived.
什么意思  他花钱雇人去杀托尼
What do you mean, he paid to have Tony killed?
派珀  慢点说  奥巴代亚为什么要
Pepper, slow down. Why would Obadiah...
好吧  托尼现在在哪
Okay, where's Tony now?
我不知道  他不接电话
I don't know. He's not answering his phone.
请你过去一趟  确保他没事
Please go over there and make sure everything's okay.
谢谢  罗德  我知道条近路
Thank you, Rhodey. I know a shortcut.
乖
Good boy.
托尼
Tony?
Tony!
托尼
托尼  你没事吧
Tony! You okay?
派珀呢
Where's Pepper?
她没事  她身边有五个特工呢
She's fine. She's with five agents.
他们要去逮捕奥巴代亚了
They're about to arrest Obadiah.
那不够
That's not going to be enough.
16区
Section 16.
在那儿呢
There it is.
我的钥匙没用  打不开门
My key's not working. It's not opening the door.
那是什么  小装置吗
What's that? It's, like, a little device?
能开锁吗
It's, like, a thing that's going to pick the lock?
你最好退后几步
You might want to take a few steps back.
那真是我见过的最酷的东西
That's the coolest thing I've ever seen.
不赖吧
Not bad, huh?
我们来吧
Let's do it.
还需要我做什么吗
You need me to do anything else?
别让人上天搅局
Keep the skies clear.
我去
Damn!
下次吧  宝贝
Next time, baby.
看来你是对的  他是在造战衣
Looks like you were right. He was building a suit.
我以为会更大些呢
I thought it'd be bigger.
干掉他
Take him out!
你觉得马克1号的胸膛电源能不能撑得住
How do you think the Mark I chest piece is going to hold up?
战衣电力为48%  还在减少  先生
The suit's at 48% power and falling, sir.
这块胸膛电源不是设计用来飞行的
That chest piece was never designed for sustained flight.
随时通知我情况
Keep me posted.
派珀
Pepper!
托尼  你没事吧
Tony! Tony, are you okay?
我没事  你怎么...
I'm fine. How are...
-奥巴代亚  他疯了  -我知道
- Obadiah, he's gone insane! - I know.
-你最好赶紧走  -他建了套战衣
- Listen, you'd better get out of there. - He built a suit.
快点  马上走
Get out of there right now!
你想去哪
Where do you think you're going?
我不再需要你的服务了
Your services are no longer required.
斯坦尼
Stane!
我爱这套战衣
I love this suit!
-把他们放下  -附带伤害  托尼
- Put them down! - Collateral damage, Tony.
向胸膛转移能量
Divert power to chest RT.
能量仅剩19%
Power reduced to 19%.
女士
Lady!
不不不
No, no, no, no, no, no!
30年了  我一直捧着你
For 30 years, I've been holding you up!
我从零建立起了这家公司
I built this company from nothing!
什么都别想妨碍我
Nothing is going to stand in my way.
你更别想
Least of all you!
厉害  你升级了你的盔甲
Impressive! You've upgraded your armour!
我自己也有升级
I've made some upgrades of my own!
先生  他的战衣似乎能飞
Sir, it appears that his suit can fly.
发现了  带我飞到最高高度
Duly noted. Take me to maximum altitude.
现在只有15%的电力
With only 15% power,
达到这高度的可能性
the odds of reaching that...
我会算算数  照做
I know the math! Do it!
长官  你不会相信的  那玩意回来了
Sir, you're not going to believe this. That thing is back.
接艾伦少校  集结飞机
Get me Major Allen. Scramble the jets!
不必了  各位  只是演练
Not necessary, people. Just a training exercise.
是  长官
Yes, sir.
只剩13%的电力了  先生
Thirteen percent power, sir.
继续爬升
Climb!
-11%  -继续飞
- Eleven percent. - Keep going!
-电力为7%  -在屏幕上显示就行
- Seven percent power. - Just leave it on the screen!
别说了
Stop telling me!
你的点子很棒  托尼
You had a great idea, Tony,
但我的战衣在各方面都更先进
but my suit is more advanced in every way!
你怎么解决结冰问题的
How'd you solve the icing problem?
什么结冰问题
Icing problem?
最好查看一下
Might want to look into it.
2%
Two percent.
现在在使用紧急备用电力
We are now running on emergency backup power.
-波茨  -托尼  天呐  你没事吧
- Potts! - Tony! Oh, my God, are you okay?
我快没电了
I'm almost out of power.
我得脱掉战衣  我就过去
I've got to get out of this thing. I'll be right there.
想得美
Nice try!
武器状态
Weapons status?
冲击系统下线  导弹下线
Repulsors offline. Missiles offline.
燃烧弹
Flares!
真聪明  托尼
Very clever, Tony.
-波茨  -托尼
- Potts? - Tony!
这样不行
This isn't working.
我们得过载反应堆  炸碎屋顶
We're going to have to overload the reactor and blast the roof.
-你要怎么做到  -你来做
- Well, how are you going to do that? - You're going to do it.
去中央控制台  打开所有电路
Go to the central console, open up all the circuits.
等我撤离了屋顶  就告诉你
When I get clear of the roof, I'll let you know.
你就按下主旁路按钮
You're going to hit the master bypass button.
上面的一切都会被烧毁
It's going to fry everything up here.
好  我这就进去
Okay. I'm going in now.
一定等我离开屋顶的  我给你争取点时间
Make sure you wait till I clear the roof. I'll buy you some time.
这个看上去挺重要
This looks important!
我一向不怎么喜欢这种玩意
I never had a taste for this sort of thing,
但我得承认  我非常喜欢这件战衣
but I must admit, I'm deeply enjoying the suit!
你可算超常发挥了  托尼
You finally outdid yourself, Tony!
你会让你父亲自豪的
You'd have made your father proud!
准备好了  托尼  快离开屋顶
It's ready, Tony! Get off the roof!
托尼
Tony!
真是讽刺  托尼
How ironic, Tony!
你想让世界上不再有武器
Trying to rid the world of weapons,
却发明了最棒的武器
you gave it its best one ever!
-派珀  -现在
- Pepper! - And now
我要拿它杀了你
I'm going to kill you with it!
-你扯掉了我的瞄准系统  -按按钮
- You ripped out my targeting system! - Time to hit the button!
-你叫我别按的  -别动  你个小混蛋
- You told me not to! - Hold still, you little prick!
-动手吧  -你会死的
- Just do it! - You'll die!
按吧
Push it!
托尼
Tony!
各位都拿到了昨晚斯塔克工业
You've all received the official statement of
詹姆斯·罗德中校  斯塔克工业事件
事件经过的官方报告
what occurred at Stark lndustries last night.
有未经证实的报告称
There have been unconfirmed reports
一件机器人原型机发生故障
that a robotic prototype malfunctioned
导致方舟反应堆受损
and caused damage to the arc reactor.
幸好  托尼·斯塔克的一位私人保镖
Fortunately, a member of Tony Stark's personal security staff...
钢铁侠是谁
"钢铁侠"  挺上口  挺响亮的
"Iron Man." That's kind of catchy. It's got a nice ring to it.
虽然并不准确
I mean, it's not technically accurate.
战衣是金钛合金
The suit's a gold-titanium alloy,
但这种意向呼之欲出
but it's kind of evocative, the imagery, anyway.
这是你的不在场证明
Here's your alibi.
好
Okay.
-你在你的游艇上  -嗯
- You were on your yacht. - Yeah.
我们有港口报告证明你整晚都在阿瓦隆
We have port papers that put you in Avalon all night,
还有你50位宾客的宣誓证词
and sworn statements from 50 of your guests.
或许该说只有我和派珀
See, I was thinking maybe we should say it was just Pepper and me
单独在岛上
alone on the island.
-就是这样的  -好吧
- That's what happened. - All right.
照读就行
Just read it, word for word.
上面没提斯坦尼
There's nothing about Stane here.
这已经处理好了  他去度假了
That's being handled. He's on vacation.
小型飞机的安全记录很差
Small aircraft have such a poor safety record.
但关于保镖的那套掩护说辞呢
But what about the whole cover story that it's a bodyguard?
他是我的...这...
He's my... I mean, is that...
这太站不住脚了吧
That's kind of flimsy, don't you think?
我不是第一次做这种事了  斯塔克先生
This isn't my first rodeo, Mr Stark.
按官方说辞念就行
Just stick to the official statement,
很快  这一切都会过去了
and soon, this will all be behind you.
你有90秒
You've got 90 seconds.
科尔森特工
Agent Coulson?
我想说  非常感谢你的一切帮助
I just wanted to say thank you very much for all of your help.
这是我们的职责  我们还会再联系的
That's what we do. You'll be hearing from us.
-你们叫国土战略  -喊我们神盾局就行
- From the Strategic Homeland... - Just call us S.H.I.E.L.D.
好
Right.
我们开始吧
Let's get this show on the road.
其实也没那么糟
You know, it's actually not that bad.
就连我都不觉得自己像钢铁侠
Even I don't think I'm Iron Man.
-你不是钢铁侠  -我是
- You're not Iron Man. - Am so.
-你不是  -好吧  随你
- You're not. - All right, suit yourself.
如果我是钢铁侠
You know, if I were Iron Man,
我会有个知道我真实身份的女友
I'd have this girlfriend who knew my true identity.
而且她会很崩溃
She'd be a wreck,
因为她会非常担心我会不会送命
'cause she'd always be worrying that I was going to die,
但又为我的成就感到骄傲
yet so proud of the man I'd become.
她会非常矛盾  而这又让她更加
She'd be wildly conflicted, which would only make her more
为我疯狂了
crazy about me.
你难道就没想过那晚的事吗
Tell me you never think about that night.
-哪一晚  -你知道的
- What night? - You know.
你是说
Are you talking about
我们一起跳舞的那晚吗
the night that we danced
然后我们上了屋顶
and went up on the roof,
然后
and then
你去楼下拿酒
you went downstairs to get me a drink,
然后就撇下了我一人
and you left me there, by myself?
你是说那晚吗
Is that the night you're talking about?
我猜也是
Thought so.
没有别的事了吧  斯塔克先生
Will that be all, Mr Stark?
是的  没别的事了  波茨小姐
Yes, that will be all, Miss Potts.
现在  斯塔克先生准备了一份声明
And now, Mr Stark has prepared a statement.
他不会接受提问的  谢谢
He will not be taking any questions. Thank you.
自我上次见大家过去好一阵了
Been a while since I was in front of you.
我这次还是照稿读吧
I figure I'll stick to the cards this time.
有人猜测
There's been speculation
我卷入了之前发生在
that I was involved in the events that occurred
高速和屋顶上的事件
on the freeway and the rooftop...
抱歉  斯塔克先生
I'm sorry, Mr Stark,
你真的指望我们相信
but do you honestly expect us to believe that
那是一个穿战衣的保镖  碰巧出现
that was a bodyguard in a suit that conveniently appeared,
-尽管你...  -我知道情况让人糊涂
- despite the fact that you... - I know that it's confusing.
质疑官方说辞是一回事
It is one thing to question the official story,
但提出疯狂指控  或暗示说
and another thing entirely to make wild accusations,
我是个超级英雄可是另一码事了
or insinuate that I'm a superhero.
我可没说你是超级英雄
I never said you were a superhero.
是吗  那很好
Didn't? Well, good,
因为那是不着边际  异想天开的
because that would be outlandish and fantastic.
我显然不是做英雄的料
I'm just not the hero type. Clearly.
我有一堆性格缺陷
With this laundry list of character defects,
犯过那么多错误
all the mistakes I've made,
-还很公开  -照稿读就行
- largely public. - Just stick to the cards, man.
好  好
Yeah, okay. Yeah.
事实就是
The truth is
我就是钢铁侠
I am Iron Man.
贾维斯
Jarvis!
欢迎回家  先生
Welcome home, sir.
"我就是钢铁侠"
"I am Iron Man."
你以为你是这世上唯一的超级英雄吗
You think you're the only superhero in the world?
斯塔克先生
Mr Stark,
你已经成为了更大的宇宙的一部分
you've become part of a bigger universe.
你只是现在还不知道
You just don't know it yet.
你是谁
Who the hell are you?
尼克·弗瑞  神盾局局长
Nick Fury, Director of S.H.I.E.L.D.
我来跟你谈谈复仇者联盟
I'm here to talk to you about the Avenger Initiative.